(bright music)
- [Narrator] The great British love affair
with train travel is as old
as the railways themselves.
From the beating heart
of London's metropolis
to the majesty of the Scottish Highlands,
connecting coast and countryside
with our great cities,
the East Coast line has it all.
(record scratching)
(bell clanging)
- Disregard that. It's a glitch.
- [Narrator] But it's
the people who give life
to this railway.
(whistle blasts)
- I won't frisk you. I trust you.
- British public are the best form
of entertainment in the planet.
(hen party cheering)
(whistle blows)
- [Narrator] The East Coast line carries
19 million passengers a year,
on 155 train journeys a day,
along almost 1000 miles of track.
The East Coast is the
largest operator on the line.
It runs trains, manages stations,
and employs nearly 3000 staff.
- That's all you're doing all day.
- I'm not playing with you
while you're showing off.
- [Narrator] The East Coast
workforce toils tirelessly-
- Mind your backs, please!
- from driving trains-
- Look at this office window. Fantastic.
- [Narrator] to making breakfasts...
- I've cooked that much
bacon over the years.
I'm surprised I haven't turned into a pig.
- [Narrator] to controlling
the whole train set.
- It's boarding. That's
absolutely excellent, Graham.
- [Narrator] Keeping everything on track
behind the scenes and in public.
- I've been standing
here for half an hour.
- [Narrator] These are the
real heroes of the railway.
(whistle blows)
(upbeat rock music)
(horn blaring)
(train whooshing)
(bright music)
East Coast Trains is a huge operation.
Behind the scenes, a dedicated
workforce grafts 24/7
to keep everything on track.
- We are the unsung heroes of the railway.
- [Narrator] And on the front line
is an army of devoted ambassadors-
(door thuds)
- I'll put your suitcase in,
just so you're not standing.
- [Narrator] From whistleblowers-
(whistle blows)
to breakfast chefs.
- Ah me bacon.
- [Narrator] These guys and gals are
the public face of the railway,
and they're primed for every eventuality.
- Apparently there's
some suspicious youths
just up round the cycle racks.
- Ah look, your coat's all undone.
- [Narrator] Highly trained
to deal with the best-
- If anybody wants the
paper I'll leave it here.
- [Narrator] And the worst that we,
Joe Public, can throw at them.
- If you did this on an airline,
you'd get to your destination
and you'd be arrested.
- [Narrator] It's their job
to keep calm and carry on.
- They reckon there's
a total loss of power.
But being a Friday it couldn't get worse.
- [Narrator] Through good times and bad.
(staff laughing)
(babbling nonsensically)
(door clunks)
- That's the last train I'll
ever dispatch in my life.
(hen party cheering)
(train rumbling)
(horn hoots)
- I had one guy who said,
"Can I have a poached egg?"
And I said, "No you
can't have a poached egg,
I says because we've only got omelettes.
I do apologise, sir."
And he went, "No, no."
He says, "I don't think you understand.
Can I have a poached egg?"
And I went, "I don't know
what you don't understand
that I've only got omelettes."
And I had to say it quite sternly.
And he went, "Really?
Don't they come from the
same place of chicken?"
And I went, "Well they
do, but," (chuckles)
I says, "they're not made on a train.
So the omelettes are made
and then they're brought on
and I regenerate them."
And he went, "So you
don't do poached eggs?"
And I just went: "No. No, mate no."
(light blues music)
- [Narrator] All aboard the
full English breakfast club.
Dishing up over 16,000 fry-ups
a year are top chef, Mark
and customer service assistant, Karen.
- Morning.
Did you place an order
with the chef this morning?
- I did.
- What did you order?
There we go. And for you, sir.
- Thank you.
- Alright, alright, whoa!
Any tomato sauce or brown sauce?
Thank you very much, cheers.
(sanguine music)
(ticker board clacking)
It's 04:20 in the morning! (laughs)
Mark is always very tired at this point
and I'm always very alive.
- Yeah.
- Morning, you alright?
We're on the 045 from Newcastle
to London Kings Cross this morning.
We stop at Durham,
Darlington, Northallerton,
York, Doncaster, Newark, North
Gate, Grantham, Peterborough,
and then London Kings Cross.
So nine stops.
Nine stops, yeah. Nine stops! (laughs)
And eight of them we pick
up and we do a service from.
(vibrant music)
- [Narrator] East Coast
services start at 4:45 a.m.
catering for sleep-staved commuters.
16 members of staff rose well before dawn
to get this Newcastle to
London train up and running.
- Coming alive now, I'm coming alive.
- [Narrator] Despite
the cosy cooking area,
Mark still has five
different breakfast dishes
up his sleeve.
- Karen, I hit the bits on the rostis
so I'll just smooth the rosti down.
(laughs) Do you know what I mean?
- [Narrator] Conditions may be cramped
but Mark wouldn't want
to chef anywhere else.
- You've got your bonus
that this is a fantastic job
and you've got your job
security because you know,
you refer to the railway
as a job for life as well
because you just feel very secure
in your job on the railway.
(upbeat rock music)
Whoo, it's smoky!
- [Sue] That was my toast.
- This is typical-
- This is my toast.
- This is Sue toast.
It's lovely as you can see.
- I was distracted.
- [Narrator] When the
heat's on in the kitchen,
it's often Karen' who keeps
her eye on quality control.
- You could never, ever
serve anybody that could you?
(ticket machine clacking)
(light clicks)
(bell pings)
(horn toots)
(train rumbling)
(gentle music)
- I went to the job centre
and they said to me,
"We've got two jobs here.
Either one be a butcher
or one join the railway."
And I thought well, transport
sounds interesting to me.
None of my family or relatives
have ever been on the railway.
I'm the first person in the
family to work on the railway.
So I thought I'll go for it.
(gentle music continues)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] 47, yes, 47
years after taking that job,
JR is now one of the York
team's longest serving members.
He's done almost every job at the station.
But the thing he loves
best is dispatching trains.
And over his 5 decade long career,
JR has sent off over 50,000 services.
- [JR] You want to be further along there.
You want to be further down,
further down.
- [Narrator] Today is
a very important day-
- [JR] 08:43.
- [Narrator] Because after
all those years on the job,
JR is retiring.
- Hello, Graham.
- Is this your last day?
- It is.
I thought you were... Is that for me?
- [Graham] Yeah.
- Thank you very much.
- I'll miss ya.
- Oh, you're a big mate of mine.
(upbeat harmonica music)
- [Narrator] And one of York's regulars,
train-spotter Graham,
is determined to mark
this momentous occasion.
- Oh my god.
(paper tearing)
It's like Christmas all over.
Oh, This looks interesting.
Let's see what it is.
A decanter, oh that's nice.
Thank you very much, Graham.
- Remember to fill it
with Scottish whisky.
- I will do now.
That's me card.
Beautiful.
I'll treasure that.
"Good luck, Goodbye from
Graham, train-spotter."
Thank you very much. I appreciate that.
- Yeah, I will miss him but
life goes on, doesn't it?
- [Narrator] For JR, it's going to be
a long and emotional final day.
(upbeat music)
(train tracks clacking)
It's hen and stag-tastic
at Newcastle station.
(stag group laughing)
Until disaster strikes.
- We reckon there's a total loss of power.
- Never happens at the quietest of times.
(whistle blows)
(train tracks clacking)
(upbeat banjo music)
(horn blaring)
- [Narrator] Spanning
the length of Britain,
the East Coast line clocks up
19 million passenger journeys a year.
It's staff have seen it all.
- I had a lady come into the station
and I could see she was like
holding her face like this.
And her husband ran over and he went,
"Excuse me! Excuse me!"
I went, "What's the
problem? Can I help you?"
He went, "Me wife's glass
eye has popped out."
He went, "Its on the track!"
What had happened was her son was going
away in the army or something
and she'd cried that much
that the eye had popped out.
We took it back up and I
actually helped the lady wash it
and she put it back in.
And I never laughed all the way through
but it wasn't until
later on Glen said to me,
"You kept your face straight
all the way through that."
He said, "You even washed her glass eye."
He went, "If that's not
going the extra mile,
I don't know what is."
(whimsical music)
- [Narrator] Jumping
eyeballs are not the only
bizarre items the East Coast
staff have to contended with.
- We've had wooden legs, all
sorts in our lost property.
Blow up dolls, everything.
- [Narrator] At York station,
Julie's been directing trains
and playing mum to
passengers for 14 years.
- What you done, lost your bag?
- Yeah, I've lost all my bags.
- Where's your case?
- Don't need a case.
- Oh, you're just going for a day?
- I'm goin' to the Shard tower.
- Oh look, your coat's
all undone, all not right.
- Well...
- There you go.
- [Passenger] I need an emergency toilet.
But it's at the top.
- Oh.
(whimsical music)
(door thuds)
(doors thudding)
(whistle blows)
- [Narrator] Julie's
duties are wide and varied,
and she's used to dealing
with the unexpected.
- From leaving their
children on the platform,
people collapsing, injuries, everything.
I just love that every day is different.
You get disruption and it's just lovely.
(upbeat country music)
(train rumbling)
(horn blaring)
- [Narrator] Today it's not so happy Abbey
who's caused the disruption.
- Just letting you know
I'm gonna be a bit late
'cause I've been an idiot
and dropped my bags down the train line.
All right I'll see you when I can.
- Did it just slip out of your hand?
- It was on here and I lifted it off.
I was an idiot and had
my bag on my suitcase
and lifted it up to get into the carriage
and it just fell down.
Nightmare.
- [Narrator] It may be
just a little handbag
but any item on the track
signals major disruption.
- Hello its Julie Garnet.
Stop the services coming
through platform three
while I'm on the track.
Yes please.
Thank you. Bye.
I've got my high-visible vest on
and I've got my boots on, trousers.
I don't want to go down with a skirt on,
show all my legs.
(upbeat country music)
- I'm a hairdresser so all of
my equipment's all in my bag.
I missed my train now.
I'm on my way to do a
photo shoot in Sheffield.
I'm such an idiot.
I feel really bad. (laughs)
(upbeat country music continues)
- [Narrator] With an entire
track out of service,
Julie leaps into action.
- There you go.
- Thank you so much.
- Alright.
- [Narrator] You're welcome Abbey.
That's all part of the service.
- All done and the
lady's got her bag back.
(key clunks)
(ticket punch whirs)
(bell pings)
(train rumbling)
(vibrant music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] Newcastle: a
mecca for stag and hen parties.
(hen shouts indistinctly)
(hens cheering)
It's the last Friday of the month,
payday.
And hundreds of revellers
are arriving at the station
for the start of a big night out.
- Here we go!
- [Narrator] On the
platform tonight is Daz,
a man who's come across
so many crazy costumes,
he could open a fancy dress shop.
- It was last year or the year before,
there was two tiger suits in lost property
and they'd been left by
obviously some stag party.
So me and Mark put these tiger suits on
and ran around the station.
It was just absolutely funny as owt.
Everybody was cracking up laughing.
It was me and Collier
just running around in these tiger suits.
It was a right laugh.
(whistle blows)
(upbeat rock music)
- [Narrator] From early afternoon
there are hens aplenty
flouncing on and off trains.
- Are ya gettin' married, mate?
- [Narrator] And ever alert
to the call to action,
Banana Man,
(stags cackling)
who is less alert than
a superhero should be.
- Always wear clean pants, kids,
in case you get hit by a car.
- I was going to say should we let you go,
But he wasn't packing much there. (laughs)
(whimsical electro reggae music)
- [Narrator] Daz has been working
at Newcastle station for 12 years,
and payday Friday shifts
are always the liveliest.
- The problems we get
with stag and hen parties,
we get a lot of delay of
trains because what they do is,
they obviously just sit
until the very last moment
and they hear the
announcements on the train
but they're not really paying attention.
Then when the train stops,
they're like looking out the window
and they can see the
Newcastle sign and it's like,
"We're here."
Alright girls I'll have to rush you.
(whimsical reggae music)
I've had incidents where people
have put their windows down
and they've actually physically
dived out onto the platform
'cause obviously they've
realised that it's their station.
- That's the bride to be.
- [Daz] What the hell you got in that?
- [Narrator] Daz has his hands full
with a station full of party animals.
- I was gonna say. (laughs)
- [Narrator] But his shift is about to get
a whole lot harder.
(distorted radio message)
(destination board clacking)
(tense music)
- [Narrator] 90 miles south
at East Coast control centre,
there's high drama.
A lightening bolt has
hit some of the signals,
and this could mean chaos for the network,
and for Daz.
- East Coast Control, Robin speaking.
(phone ringing)
Basically at about 3 o'clock
there was a thunderstorm
south of Berwick that's knocked
out some of the signalling.
What we've had to do is
cancel trains at Edinburgh,
and cancel trains at Newcastle,
to stop sending trains
towards the affected area.
(upbeat electro music)
- We reckon there's a total loss of power.
So the next two trains
I think will make it in
and then we might have nothing for awhile.
- [Narrator] Delays are
bad at the best of times,
but on a busy Friday, they're disastrous.
17 trains an hour, each
carrying around 400 passengers,
are scheduled to pass
through Newcastle today.
With the service stalled,
disgruntled passengers will
not only get stuck on board,
thousands could also start to pile up
on the station platforms.
- And you're talking tens
of thousands of passengers
packed into the doorways as well.
And obviously it's rammed;
we've just got a sea of
passengers everywhere.
- A lot of people going home
for the weekend et cetera,
going away for the weekend.
You know, Sod's law, but
that's the way it is.
It never happens at the quietest of times.
- [Narrator] Looks like
Daz's Payday Friday
could become the shift from hell!
(tone beeps)
(punch clicks)
(whistle blows)
(relaxed blues music)
In York, veteran of the railways, JR,
has seen his fair share
of crisis management.
But today his shift is not
about controlling chaos,
it's about saying goodbye.
- There's three teams on York station,
and to me it's like my family.
So I meet 'em regular,
go for a drink or see 'em somewhere,
go round to see 'em at their
house, have a drink with them.
Oh yeah they'll all keep friendly,
yeah always be there, always be my mates.
- All the best to you
darling. You take care.
- When I left me house this
morning I thought it's weird.
But now I come back here
at 2 o'clock or whatever
I've finished.
- That's it.
- And this gentleman here
is always giving me mints.
Aren't you? He looks after
me on the sweet department.
See you later.
- [Narrator] There's one person who means
more to him than all the rest:
his teammate of 17 years
and current boss, Paola.
(warm, gentle music)
- JR is loved honestly by everybody here.
He's just always been the same.
He comes into work positive, upbeat,
always the same.
Never, never sad.
- Oh what's that?
Forever Friends.
And we will be.
We will be always friends for
the rest of our lives, Paola.
- Okay.
- Alright.
- Enjoy today.
- I know what'll happen now I'm going,
change the locks.
(laughs) I'm only joking.
"Hey, Gaggy, keep him out."
They've changed all t'locks.
"He's gone. Change 'em." (laughs)
That's it.
- We do actually change the codes
on the door when people leave. (chuckles)
But that's just what we do as
part of process and security.
But he'll never be,
he'll never be shut out.
- [Narrator] As one of
Paola's team takes his leave,
another new recruit's life on the railway
is just beginning.
- I was in my previous
role as a fish monger
and one of my customers was
Paola, the station manager now.
And liked what she saw in me,
thought I'd be good at the job.
I got, you could say poached,
it's a massive change for me.
But it's the best decision
I ever made to be honest.
(inquisitive music)
- [Narrator] Paola might have poached Liam
away from the salmon, but
he's got a lot to prove
before he's ready to
dispatch trains like JR.
At the moment his main
task is station security.
- Every hour I have to do
a full lap of the station.
So I'm looking for anything suspicious,
any hidden packages,
all in the platforms, the travel centre,
the car parks, the bike racks.
I've got to check all that within one hour
and I've got to do that
every hour for my full shift.
(funky upbeat music)
- [Narrator] Railway rookie Liam
has to be extra-specially vigilant.
(toilet flushing)
- Apparently there's
some suspicious youths
just up round the cycle racks
a few minutes ago, drinking.
I don't think they were
probably old enough to drink,
but the police are on their way anyways.
I'm pretty sure they've cleared off.
But I have to go down this
platform anyway, so...
The police have gone around
the bike racks as well
so it's just to check that those youths
have definitely cleared off,
which it appears they have.
At random intervals also,
the department of transport,
they will come and test us.
They can and quite often
do plant something.
So last time it was a
small black hold-all.
But they give us two
hours really to find it.
So they're the hide and
seek experts really.
- [Producer] Did you
find it on that occasion?
- The last time, no I didn't.
(funky upbeat music)
So I really feel the pressure
now to make sure next time
they come that I've got find it.
So everyone will think, "Yeah,
Liam's great at his job,
Liam's gonna find it.
If Liam's on duty we know we're safe."
Yeah, no worries, Paola.
I'm on platform seven but
I'll make my way over.
Over.
(radio crackles)
- [Narrator] Liam's been called
to check a security alert.
(indistinct radio alert)
- Just had a message of
some unattended luggage
at the front of the station.
So this is when I come in use for them.
So I have to have a look at that.
- [Narrator] The unattended
bag could represent
a major security threat.
Liam is straight on the case.
- Let's have a look.
Yeah as predicted, pretty much nothing.
Nothing.
No, I think we're all clear.
Safe to fight another day.
(upbeat music)
(train whooshing)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] Problems
pile up on payday Friday.
- And the more build up
of passengers there is,
then it becomes really dangerous.
- [Narrator] And while the hens
make the best of a bad day-
(hens cheering)
it could be game over for the stags.
- The only person who
caught the last train north
was the stag.
(jaunty banjo music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] It's Payday
Party Friday in Newcastle
and Information Controller
Daz is in the middle
of one of the most stressful
shifts of his year.
Everybody wants to start their weekend
but thousands of passengers
are going nowhere fast.
- All I'm gonna do is
ask you to wait awhile.
There's nothing moving at the
moment north of Newcastle.
So if you have a seat in the
waiting room on the platforms.
As soon as we know something,
we're gonna come round
but listen to our
announcements as well, yeah.
Have a seat in the waiting room
or have a seat on the platform.
As soon as we know we'll let yous know.
Listen for announcements,
though, madam, okay?
- [Passenger] Alright, thanks very much.
(upbeat rock music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] 90 miles south
in the central control room,
it's controlled chaos because of an
unexpected lightning strike.
- 45 minutes.
Who am I to stop thunder and lightning?
I'm afraid, you know, that does happen.
The systems short out.
We don't tender with a situation unsafe
and we don't tender with a
train heading into an area
where there is no signalling at all.
(jaunty music)
(train rattling)
- [Narrator] Four trains
heading north from Kings Cross,
and three trains heading
south from Scotland
have all been stopped in their tracks.
- There's a waiting room there
if you want to keep warm.
As soon as we know we'll let you know.
Cheers. Thank you.
The hardest thing is
obviously the passengers
all want to know what's going on.
I don't know anything.
(radio chatter crackles)
I'm trying to listen to that
and keep the trains
going at the same time,
as well as everybody talking.
So it makes it quite hard.
- [Narrator] Over 3,000
passengers are stuck on trains,
and the number waiting
at Newcastle station
is about to hit a thousand.
It's up to Daz to keep calm and carry on.
- I do believe there's been buses ordered
but we'll obviously have to
wait and see what happens
in the next half an hour.
- It's a good night out in
Newcastle anyway. (laughs)
- Party city, yeah. Okay.
- [Narrator] Central
control has to take action
before the situation gets worse.
- Just bear with me.
Nickola, number 1-9 is
nearly in Newcastle.
So that could form Echo 2-1.
- [Narrator] The decision
is taken to terminate
all northbound trains at Newcastle
and send them back down south,
keeping the service
running between Newcastle
and London at least.
- Right, this is the 15:58 to London.
You can get on now.
Anybody travelling on the 15:58.
- [Narrator] So for Daz, it's all change
as his northbound trains
have just become southbound.
(up-tempo dance music)
- Right let's get it
away. Let's get it away.
All right bud?
No crew? No buffet crew?
I'm not worried about the buffet crew
but we've got a guard and a driver.
That'll do yeah.
Cheers though. Thank you.
(upbeat rock music)
(whistle blows)
- [Narrator] With the Southbound
passengers out of his hair,
Daz still has to deal with
the northbound passengers
stranded on the other platforms.
Their trains are still not running,
but although many are all
dressed up with nowhere to go,
some have come prepared.
(hens singing and laughing)
- We've got some gin and tins
and we're just having a party.
- Train's delayed but we're
making the most of it.
- We're having the hen
party on the station.
- -We're having a platform party.
My little sister is getting
married so every guy around
is gonna be crying their eyes out
because this beautiful lady is taken.
Well done, Nicki.
(all cheering)
- [Narrator] Cheers, ladies.
If only lads were as well organised.
- We're here on a stag do.
22 people,
the only person that
caught the last train north
was the stag, who is
now at Edinburgh station
on his own in a kilt,
dressed like Mel Gibson.
He looks a state and he's on his own.
We're all a bit sad for him.
The one rule,
the one rule is that no
one leaves the stag alone,
and 21 other people left the stag alone.
We have completely dropped the ball.
- We don't know what to do now.
We don't know how to get to Edinburgh.
We're completely lost.
- (chuckles) You've got me.
- Rebecca here doesn't know what to do.
- We have Rebecca. We met Rebecca.
(languid acoustic music)
(bustle of passengers)
- [Narrator] So far Daz has
managed to keep a cool head.
But as the disruption continues,
he starts to feel the pressure.
- The more trains that
come in and terminate,
the more passengers
we're going to have here.
As you can see from
them, there's quite a lot
of people close to the
edges and that, you know.
And the more buildup
of passengers there is,
then it becomes really dangerous
and it's obviously a concern, you know.
But being a Friday, it couldn't get worse.
It can't get worse than a Friday.
(socket wrench clicks)
(printer whirs)
(keyring jingles)
(upbeat music)
(train clacking)
- [Narrator] 270 miles away,
down south at King's Cross,
self-confessed trolley-dolly Jack
is preparing for show time!
(confident upbeat music)
Jack used to fancy treading the boards,
but since starting his job on the railway,
he's realised there's no
more captive an audience
than one trapped on a train
(horn blaring)
- If I'm there and I'm having fun
and I'm talking to the customers
and I'm being a bit show-bizzy
and having a bit of fun with them,
then that makes my day go quicker.
If they're then enjoying their journey
because I'm being a bit silly,
then that makes their
journey go a bit quicker.
Everyone has a nicer day.
Good evening ladies and gentlemen.
My name is Jack Allen,
catering crew leader for your journey.
I did performing arts
when I was in college
as an A-level.
So I mean maybe, it
probably stems from that.
For those passengers in standard class
who do wish to remain seated,
the trolley service is making
its way through the train.
Yeah that's my stage. (laughs)
Any teas, coffees, cold drinks?
(upbeat rock music)
♪ Na, na-na-na ♪
♪ Na-na, na-na-na ♪
- Just make sure that's
actually the right items;
that I haven't charged you
for something you've not got.
That okay? No worries.
I'll chuck that way for you if you want.
It's not part of the receipt.
I just like going through
chatting rubbish to people.
I do it to confuse people.
(Jack chuckling)
I know what I'm doing. Professional, me.
Any refreshments at all?
Oops, sorry.
I'm throwing milk at people now.
It's alright, I won't
drop that one on you.
That'd be really mean of me.
It's kind of like manoeuvring
a full shopping cart down,
well, down a moving train.
Sorry, is that your bag there sir?
- Yeah. Sorry.
- Sorry, that's alright.
This is quite heavy, I don't
want to damage anything.
Until you get the hang of it,
you're constantly crashing
into people's seats
and nearly running people over,
which most people tend
not to be too happy about.
(upbeat music)
- [Narrator] And while
mastering his trolley act,
Jack's bumped into all sorts.
- We actually had Prince Philip travelling
with sort of six or seven of
his security detail. (laughs)
who were mildly terrifying.
I was very worried that I
would get something wrong.
I was worried the train would jolt
and I would get coffee everywhere.
Luckily that didn't happen.
I did that really awkward
and annoying thing,
that when you're talking to
someone, your voice breaks.
So, "Can I get you any
(squeaks) coffee sir?"
Oh no.
(upbeat music resumes)
- [Narrator] Eagle eyed staff might even
get to spot their favourite
celeb somewhere along the line
- Hugh Grant was trying
to get into the toilet
which was closed for painting.
So I took my chance, ran up,
asked him if he'd like to use the toilet
and took him upstairs to the office.
I found myself in the
staff kitchen with him.
He asked me where the toilet was
and when I went to show him,
nothing came out of my mouth
because I was so sort of in awe.
We have a sign on the back
of the toilet door now:
Hugh Grant sat here.
(bright reggae music)
- [Narrator] It's not just Hollywood stars
and royalty who frequent
the East Coast line.
- We're on the 11:00 from
Kings Cross to Edinburgh
and Sting's up there.
I think I've got a bit of
an eye for it if I'm honest.
Its not that I'm on the look
out but I usually do pick up
pretty quickly if I see someone famous.
(bright reggae music)
(train rumbling)
- Missed him unfortunately
but Paul McCartney
was on station a few weeks ago.
- Bobby Robson, I might
add he's fantastic.
He was in when, obviously
before he passed away.
- Jeremy Paxman, I used to
work at Berwick for a while.
He was really nice,
a big bloke, like, a really tall bloke.
You know when you get to see
people in like real life,
you don't realise how
some of them are small
or some of them are really big, you know.
- [Narrator] And some of
them are larger than life.
- If anybody wants the
paper I'll leave it here.
Recycled.
Thank you for the lovely journey again.
- [Narrator] Bye-di-bye, Sue.
- Next leg of the journey: Skegness!
Bye.
(lock clicks)
(ticket scrapes)
(glass clinks)
(horn blaring)
(lively fiddle music)
- [Narrator] Keeping cool with
famous faces is one thing,
but one VIP who gets
everybody hot under the collar
is a customer so important
they have to go completely incognito.
She, who shall not be named or even seen,
is what's known as a - [Mystery Shopper]
mysterious by name and blurry by nature.
- Can I just say something to you?
I've no idea...
- Today it's Bianca,
Jack and Beth's turn to be spied on.
But they don't even know it.
- I'm definitely a people
person as you can probably tell.
I can't stop talking so
it's the perfect job for me.
I just enjoy it 'cause
every day is different.
You never meet the same sort of people.
- Bianca and I get on well.
She talks an awful lot
but then that's Bianca.
- [Narrator] They think they could spot
an undercover agent a mile off.
- You can tell. You can tell.
- Some of them can be sort of obvious.
They'll be writing things down,
they'll be sitting in certain carriages.
- [Beth] And they'll
ask for specialty teas.
- Yeah, the ones that go the extra mile
but then ask you to sort of,
"Oh can I have a bottle of water?"
And you say, "Yeah no problem;
I'll bring that down for you."
And as long as you bring it back.
So they know things like that.
- [Narrator] But today Bianca and Beth's
secret service radar is way off course.
- Hello. Can I get you anything
to drink or some biscuits?
- [Mystery Shopper] Yeah.
Have you got any apple juice?
- Unfortunately I've only
got orange this morning.
- I'll have orange please.
- Orange, okay?
Any biscuits for you?
- No thank you.
- There you go.
Thank you very much.
- Thank you.
- We had one guy that was on once.
We were going to Leeds.
He came up from London,
got off at Wakefield,
we came straight back half an hour later
and he got back on again.
We were sort of all
stood on the train going,
"I don't think you did much
while you were in Wakefield, did you?"
But most of the time you can't
really tell who they are.
(upbeat music)
- [Narrator] So, will their
customer service make the grade?
(quiet indistinct chatter)
(upbeat music continues)
Did Bianca and Beth's on-board performance
impress the mystery shopper?
- [Mystery Shopper] They
seemed like a very nice team.
They worked well together.
They worked hard.
They were good, they were really good
and they were cheerful with it
and they obviously wanted you to enjoy it.
(fast-paced music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] Daz tries
to keep his spirits up.
- I stink of booze.
Someone will probably complain
that I've been drinking.
(whistle blows)
- [Narrator] And JR
faces the final curtain.
- That's the last train I'll
ever dispatch in my life.
- Are you alright?
- Yeah.
- Aw.
(JR chuckles)
(bright music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] After 47
years of loyal service,
JR is working out his ever last shift.
That's got be worth a party!
- Oh my God.
Oh that's fantastic.
Look at this.
- Your favourites.
- My favourite is pork pies.
My god. It's fantastic.
Whoa! Oh my god.
Oh, it's fantastic.
- Party time.
JR, on behalf of us all,
we wish you the best.
Have a long and happy retirement.
- It'll be okay.
- I'll be alright.
- Right, all the best, John.
I'll see you later on.
- Thank you.
- See you later, darlin'.
- See you later.
- [JR] Oh my word.
(JR chuckling)
- Aw.
- [Narrator] But JR's
final day is far from over.
(melancholic music)
He's still got his last
ever train to dispatch.
- Alright?
- I'm feeling all right.
It's a shame it's gonna be
my last service to dispatch.
As soon as I go out to the platform,
it's my last train for the rest of my life
so it's gonna be emotional for me.
I'm very upset about it, really.
- [Narrator] JR dispatched
his first train in 1987
and he's seen off over
30 a day ever since.
- That's first stop London, sir.
Coach where, sir?
- E!
- E. There it is, just behind you.
Okay.
(melancholic music)
Here we go, me last train.
(JR blowing whistle)
Just watch it out, make sure it's okay.
(horn blaring)
He's papping his horn.
He must know it's me
last train. (chuckles)
(carriages rumbling)
(melancholic music continues)
There she goes.
(horn blaring)
That's it, aint it, Paola.
That's my last train I'll
ever dispatch in my life.
- Are you all right?
- Yeah.
- Aw.
(JR chuckles)
- Oh dear me. I'm a bit sad about that.
Anyway, I'll be all right.
- [Paola] Come on.
- [Narrator] JR's 47 years
of service to the line,
and to Joe Public, is complete.
(cutlery clanking)
(radio hisses)
(wrench squeaks)
(upbeat music)
(destination board clacking)
But back at Newcastle,
Daz's job is far from over.
It's payday and hen-and-stag-do Friday
and after two hours of
delays in both directions,
the first train from
Edinburgh finally arrives.
(stags shouting)
The train needs to be cleaned quickly
before it's turned around
and sent back down the line.
And Daz has drawn the short straw.
(upbeat rock music continues)
- Basically what's happened
here is the last stag party,
like some stag parties do,
decide to treat wor
trains, leave them a tip
and it's just disgusting, this.
I mean, these passengers,
eight passengers,
maybe ten will have to
sit in these seats now.
I'm just gonna try and
get what I can off here
just to make it look presentable at least.
But I should, I've got no tape
or I'd normally just tape the seat off.
But I mean, look at this, man.
It's unacceptable behaviour, isn't it?
If you did this on an airline,
you'd get to your destination
and you'd be arrested.
Simple as that because that's
what they do on the airlines.
But we have to put up with it.
I stink of booze.
Somebody will probably complain
that I've been drinking.
Nowt we can do, we'll
just have to get it away.
I haven't been drinking, mind.
I want to today, after all that.
(Daz blowing whistle)
(weary music)
(destination board clacking)
- [Narrator] And at long last,
there's good news from the control centre
about the north-running trains.
- 020, the 14:00 on the
Kings Cross Aberdeen
is just arriving in platform two.
So that should clear as many
northbound passengers as possible.
Trains will be running
normally between Newcastle
and Berwick in a few minutes.
(low bustling of passengers)
- [Narrator] Finally, the whole
line is up and running again
and Daz can see light at
the end of the tunnel.
- The way things are going, by about 7:00
we should have most passengers
away by then, you know.
So it should be good.
We're getting there now.
We're getting there.
Slowly but surely, we're
starting to get there, yeah.
(horn blaring)
- We're trying to get to
Edinburgh for a hen do
and the train's here!
(hens cheering)
- We've been waiting two hours now.
Two hours.
- Two hours
(hens cheering)
- The train's here!
- Yeah!
- [Narrator] But there's one
final spanner in the works.
- That's... this is the 17:25, this one.
- So is that Northallerton?
- No, disregard that.
- Okay, yeah.
- It's a glitch, alright.
That's the 17:25.
- [Narrator] The controller might say yes,
but the computer says no.
- He's gonna try and update it.
Somehow the computer thinks
it's a different train.
- Does this stop at Stevenage?
- It will be. It's the 17:25, sir.
I'm getting them to do
something about that, okay?
Howay, little man, you all right, mate?
I'll just push you to the back there
for a couple of seconds.
Alright, darling?
Let me off 'cause I haven't got a ticket.
Believe it or not, I still
have to pay for it, yeah.
- Is this the 17:25?
- It is sir, yes.
Yes, 17:25.
(upbeat music)
(door clunks)
(whistle blows)
(carriages rumbling)
- [Narrator] After an especially hectic
Friday evening shift,
no-one deserves the relief
of a weekend break more than Daz.
- We've got everything back to normal.
We're really happy,
everybody's buzzing again.
Aye, we'll see the rest
of the night out now.
And I'll be off for a
drink myself tonight,
and take my good lady for
something to eat and that, yeah.
It's payday, you know.
You've gotta dae it on
payday, eh. (laughs)
- [Narrator] With happy passengers finally
on the move from Newcastle,
(destination board clacking)
back in York there's one last surprise
for one of the station's
longest serving staff members.
- [Announcement] On behalf of East Coast
and everybody at York station,
we would like to wish JR
a very happy retirement.
(colleagues applauding)
- It's a sad day for me.
Thank you very much.
Oh, it's a sad day.
Cheers. Thank you.
(colleagues applauding)
(upbeat music)
Oh, I'm upset now.
- You alright?
- I am happy though.
Thank you all very much.
Thank you.
Oh, thank you. Thank you very much.
Cheers. Thank you all.
Thank you.
Great. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Cheers.
I won't forget you as long as I live.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Paola.
- Bye. (kisses)
- Oh, that's great.
- Come on then.
- Hey, thank you.
- JR has absolutely loved it.
He didn't expect any of the little
surprises that we gave him.
We've given him a nice
sendoff and we'll see him.
We'll look after him.
- See you later. Bye-bye.
(upbeat rock and roll music)
- Bye!
Oh!
Aw!
(upbeat rock and roll music continues)
(no audio)